A Guide to the The Papers of the Joseph Carrington Cabell Family ca. 1783-1887
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Topics in the fifth folder of correspondence from John Hartwell Cocke to Joseph Cabell include: his desire for Cabell to study the canal policy (1824 Feb 16 and Aug 5); mention of the work of Claudius Crozet and Cocke's disappointment with his mechanic Duncan (1824 Jun 19 and Nov 20); Cocke's interest in the Colonization Society (1825 Jul 19); and two letters from John Hartwell Cocke, Jr. in his father's absence (1829 Aug 19 and 31).
Topics in the sixth folder include: reference to the scandalous split between Cabinet members supporting either President Jackson or John Calhoun (1831 Mar 11); description of a local religious revival (1831 May 17); visit to Philadelphia with his family (1834 Jun 24); and a letter from John H. Cocke, Jr. about his father's plans to return home (1834 Jul 28).
Topics in the seventh folder of correspondence from John Hartwell Cocke to Joseph Cabell include: Sim's mill and the canal and concern over errors in its construction (1840 Jul 24 and 27); praise for Cabell's 7th Annual Report about the James River and Kanawha Company (1842 Jan 20); the temperance movement (1842 May 25); religious counsel (1844 May 25); and his trip to Greene County, Alabama (1844 Dec 31).
Topics in the eighth folder include: advice to the Cabells to send all their slaves to Liberia and free themselves from the worries of being a slave owner (1846 Feb 11); Cocke convinced more than ever that the causes of agricultural ruin lie in the multiplication of slavery and the cultivation of tobacco (1846 Apr 27 and 1849 Sep 20); Cocke's low opinion of Swedenborgianism (1847 Jan 21 and Feb 12); disappointment with the inaction of the Virginia General Assembly on the issue of internal improvements, particularly the extension of the canal (1847 Feb 12); Cocke's advice for Cabell to carefully train his most intelligent slave as a miller (1847 Jun 17); Cocke's opposition to the "railroad schemes" of Farland Lyons and Company to supersede the progress of the James River and Kanawha Canal Company with their own interests and his summary of the railroad meeting in Richmond (1847 Dec 3); the success of Mr. Hill's rotary fish trap (1848 Apr 14 and 26); the death of Mr. Brent (1848 Jun 6); the construction of Cocke's Fountain Temple, its completion and dedication (1848 Jul 20 and 1849 Sep 20); news and discussion of the temperance movement (1848 Jul 20, Aug 30 and 31; and 1848 Sep 8); and a letter from Mr. E.T. Bryan, forwarded to Cabell, also discussing temperance (1848 Sep 8).
Topics in the last and ninth folder of correspondence from John Hartwell Cocke to Joseph Cabell include: winter in Greene County, Alabama and Remington's Aerial Bridge construction (1850 Jan 12); Cocke's controversy with the James River & Kanawha Canal Company (1850 May 1); his request for Cabell to attend the meetings of the James River and Kanawha Canal Company stockholders (1851 Oct 20 and Nov 10; 1852 Oct 7; 1853 Oct 8); the evil effects of growing tobacco on Virginia soil, calling it the "bane of Virginia husbandry" (1852 Mar 15; 1853 Aug 13; and 1854 Mar 3); and a letter from Dr. John Augustine Smith, a fellow student with Cabell and Cocke at William and Mary, February 24, 1853 (enclosed with 1853 Apr 3).
The topics in the two folders of correspondence from Isaac A. Coles to Joseph Cabell include: a severe storm at sea near Richmond, Virginia (1802 Jan 23); description of Coles travel and experiences in France (1804 Jul 15); discussion of the prospects for war and his own future (1808 Apr 3); request that Cabell secure for him portraits of Cabell's brother and William Wirt by Charles Balthazar Julien Fevret de Saint- Memin (1808 Nov 28); Mr. Lee and his consulship at Bordeaux (1809 Nov 12); Coles' feud with Roger Nelson, whom he slapped in the Capitol building (1809 Dec 9); request to purchase some slaves from Corotoman from Cabell (1810 Feb 25); notes that Thomas Jefferson has been called away to Bedford unexpectedly (1811 Feb 12); Coles return to Washington as an officer (1812 Jan 27); reference to the financial ruin of Colonel Nicholas (1819 Aug 8); plans to travel to the Eastern Shore and Lake Drummond, with his wife (1823 Apr 22); and a cholera epidemic in Norfolk, Virginia (1832 Aug 11).
Individual folders of correspondence to Joseph C. Cabell continue in Box 5. Topics mentioned in the correspondence of Mayo Cabell to Joseph Cabell include agriculture and the condition of the canal and locks (1847 May 18). Malcolm F. Crawford of Charlottesville writes of his unsuccessful attempts to secure a workman for Joseph Cabell. William J. Lewis, a delegate and representative from Virginia, writes to Cabell of business matters and forwards copies of government documents.
Topics of note in the correspondence from Thomas S. McLelland to Joseph Cabell include: two named slave girls, Judy and Mary, belonging to Joseph Cabell and loaned to McLelland for nursing duties (1815 Apr 16); and the death of William Cabell, Jr. (1819 Jun 28). Robert Rives corresponds about the sale of Cabell's wheat and other agricultural matters.
There are a number of letters from Henry St. George Tucker to Joseph Cabell. Topics mentioned in these include: the honors bestowed upon George Washington, whose virtues outshone all of his faults, a speech by Henry Lee, the Virginia Resolutions from the pen of James Madison, a delegate in the Virginia General Assembly, and a law altering the mode of election (1800 Feb 1); controversy over the statue of Lord Botetourt and other news of William and Mary in Williamsburg, Virginia (1801 Aug 8); success in getting his law license and news of politics in Williamsburg (1802 May 7); Tucker's impressions of Winchester, Virginia and the death of Lilly Byrd (1802 Aug 26); Tucker's declaration of himself as a candidate for the General Assembly (1807 Apr 2); death of Mrs. Tucker, mother of correspondent (1837 Sep 8 and 26); and work and living arrangements for two slaves, Charles and Nancy (1838 May 9).
Letters from Charles Yancey to Joseph Cabell are chiefly concerned with social invitations and agricultural business.
The remainder of the correspondents to Joseph Cabell are individuals with fewer letters who are grouped in the Miscellaneous Correspondents alphabetical folders. These correspondents are all noted in the folder listing and only those with topics of particular note are included in these scope and content notes. Among these topics are: desire to discuss the improvement of the James River navigation (Randolph Harrison, 1819 Mar 23); revising the proof sheets of the pamphlet by Joseph Cabell (James E. Heath, 1831 Aug 8); description of the action taken by the Virginia House of Delegates and Senate on the amendment to the James River Bill (William C. Holt, 1823 Feb 25); and details about a plaster mill (Charles F. Mercer, 1820 Sep 6).
Additional topics in the Miscellaneous Correspondents include: discussion about printing and circulating some letters of James Madison (Hugh Mercer, 1829 Mar 4); discussion of the judicial system of Virginia (Charles L. Mosby, 1850 Aug 10); the death of a slave, Oscar (T. Oldham, 1849 Nov 24); description of a hemp and flax breaking machine (James Pleasants, 1822 Apr 1); quest to have his brother, Francis, appointed Elector for his district (James P. Preston, 1816 Jan 14); misunderstanding during a debate over a bill (James Robertson, 1816 Feb 6); medical advice (Dr. William Southall, 1818 Nov 18); and information about the theft of a young female slave belonging to the overseer of Joseph Cabell, Mr. Poor, supposedly stolen by Johnson alias Smith and the free "Negro" Joe Ligon, whose registry transcription is included with the letter (Colonel Park Street, 1818 Apr 8).
The second series of papers consists of the correspondence of members of the Bolling family, the Cabell family, and related families. The papers of the Bolling family, especially those of Colonel William Bolling, Goochland County, Virginia, are most likely found in this collection because William Bolling was a commissioner and agent for the James River and Kanawha Canal Company who collected subscriptions for stock in this company. Joseph C. Cabell was also heavily involved in the company as president.
Folders containing correspondence to members of the Bolling family include several letters from Jane Bolling to her father, William Bolling, while she was visiting in Washington, (Box 6); Sally F. Cabell to her brother and sister-in-law, Philip and Julia Bolling Cabell (Box 8); miscellaneous correspondents to William Bolling arranged alphabetically (Box 10); miscellaneous correspondents to the Bolling family (Box 10); and miscellaneous correspondents to Philip B. Cabell and his wife, Julia Bolling Cabell (Box 10).
Also in this series is considerable correspondence from Sally Faulcon Cocke Brent (1816-1879) to her sister, Ann Blaws Cocke Cabell (1811-1862) consisting of much news about the different families (Box 6), and ten letters from Sally Brent and her husband, Arthur Lee Brent, to her brother-in-law, Nathaniel Francis Cabell (Box 6). Both groups of letters contain some correspondence about their attitudes and activities concerning the Civil War.
Much of the remaining correspondence in this series consists of letters to and from Nathaniel Francis Cabell (1807-1891), his wife, Ann Blaws Cocke Cabell, and their immediate family members. Nathaniel Francis Cabell, who married Anne Blaws Cocke (1811-1862), the daughter of John Hartwell Cocke, in 1831, inherited the Liberty Hall estate in Nelson County, Virginia. He was the son of Nicholas (1780-1809) and Margaret Venable Cabell (1782-1857) and nephew of Joseph C. Cabell.
There are over a hundred letters from Ann Blaws Cocke Cabell to her husband (Box 6) and about eighty from Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his wife (Box 7). This collection also contains about sixty letters from Ann Cabell to her son, Philip Barraud Cabell (Box 6). There are many letters from Elizabeth Nicholas Cabell to her mother, Ann Cabell (Boxes 6-7); Philip B. Cabell to both parents (Box 8); Sally F. Cabell to her father, Nathaniel Francis Cabell (Box 8); William D. Cabell to his in-laws (Box 8); and many letters from Lucy Oliver Cocke, wife of Dr. Cary Charles Cocke, to her sister-in-law, Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell (Box 9).
Other correspondents writing to Nathaniel Francis Cabell include: Dr. John Grattan Cabell, 1861-1863, chiefly about the Civil War and the sale of a slave, Lewis, December 3, [1862?](Box 7); Mary W. Cabell, chiefly about borrowing books and the New Jerusalem Church doctrine (Box 7); H.H. Hite dealing with the depredations experienced in Virginia during the Civil War and Reconstruction and being cut off from the Northern brethren of the New Jerusalem Church because of the conflict (Box 10); Benjamin H. Magruder, Scottsville, Virginia, about the sale of property (Box 10); Cabell's cousin, Ella Floyd Mosby, chiefly about borrowing books and the New Jerusalem Church doctrine (Box 10); and Judge Francis Nathaniel Watkins (1813-1885), Farmville, Virginia, about the destruction of the Civil War, old times, religious ideas, and genealogical questions (Box 11). An obituary for Watkins can be found at the end of his letters.
Nathaniel Francis Cabell writes to his cousin, Isaac Read, discussing the loss of his wife and other family members (1862 May, 1864 May 7) and other family troubles, and his remarriage to Mary M. Kellar, of Baltimore, Maryland (1867 Oct). Cabell also describes the centennial of his school, Hampden Sidney College (1876 Aug 16) to Read (Box 8).
The correspondence of Isaac Read to Cabell can be found in Box 11. These letters discuss the issue of slavery and the sectional strife of the country (1855 Dec 9; 1860 Jun 18; 1861 Feb 10), the Civil War service of Read's sons (1861 Sep 6); the death of General Philip St. George Cocke (1862 Jan 1); the progress and destructions of the Civil War (all letters 1861-1865); Reconstruction politics (1867 Oct 16; 1868 Mar 4); his move to Brooklyn, New York, to live with his oldest son, partially to avoid the problems of Reconstruction and the utter ruin of the South (1872-1984); the location of each of his sons (1874 Sep 27; 1875 Jan 31, including ideas about the Beecher scandal; 1876 Jun 12); and his preparation for death.
Correspondence from Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his father-in-law, John Hartwell Cocke (Box 7), is concerned with the building of his house on the Liberty Hall estate, references to family slaves, agricultural advice and questions, and the business of the James River & Kanawha Canal Company. Cabell also discusses his belief and involvement in the New Jerusalem Church. For an example, see the letter from N.F. Cabell to Cocke, dated July 29, 1840. He also discusses the temperance issue, the affairs of the University of Virginia, the Sprague and Delavan controversy (1842 Apr 11), and his progress in agriculture.
Correspondence from John Hartwell Cocke to his son-in-law, Nathaniel Francis Cabell can be found in Box 9. Topics in these letters include: advice about the operation of Cabell's plantation; work on his house; the urgency of road improvement in their areas; the evils of alcohol, especially among the Irish and German laborers (1836 May 30) and the questions about use of wine in communion (1837 Feb 24); the progress of the James River and Kanawha Canal Company (1836 Dec 20; 1842 Oct 10); theological arguments (1837 Mar 26); a prescription for epilepsy (1839 Jul 19); and Cocke's opinion of Swedenborgism (1840 Aug 21).
Other topics include: an admonition to Cabell to change himself from "a reading man to a working man" in order to save his plantation and make it a paying affair (1840 Dec 3; 1841 Oct 5); advances in the temperance movement (1848 Aug-1849 Jul); notice that one vacancy may be available in Cocke's school and a list of slaves with their ages from his register (1850 Sep 4 and 30); the presidential election, the Maine Law, and request for N.F. Cabell's opinion of Uncle Tom's Cabin(1852 Nov 5); Cocke's opinion of a book on slavery called The Impending Crisis by Hinton Rowan Helper, 1829-1909, (1857 Oct 2); and his attempt to find out if Philip B. Cabell has accepted the position as military aid to Philip St. George Cocke (1861 Aug 20).
Letters from Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his son, Philip Barraud Cabell, in the first folder were chiefly written while Philip was being educated at the school at Bremo, Fluvanna County, and then at the University of Virginia, 1853-1857 and are full of admonishment and fatherly advice. The second folder contains letters during the Civil War period, 1861-1863, one mentioning the condition of the slaves at the hospital in Richmond (1863 Oct 28), and other letters to Philip after he had moved to Urbana, Ohio, to teach at the Urbana University in 1875. Among these is a letter about the sale of the Laneville estate, located about a mile below Warminster, Nelson County, Virginia, and the troubles of the family (1875 Oct 5).
Many of the letters of Philip B. Cabell were written to his parents while he was away from home for educational purposes. There are also letters written during the Civil War in the second folder of his correspondence, describing his military service as a volunteer aide to General Philip St. George Cocke (see time of service document, Oct 1861).
The interest of Nathaniel Francis Cabell in the writings of Emanuel Swendenborg and the New Jerusalem Church, in which he was baptized in 1842 by the Reverend Richard De Charms of Baltimore, Maryland, is illustrated in this collection by his correspondence with and about the Reverend George Bush (Boxes 6 and 8) and with the Reverend Richard De Charms (Boxes 8 and 9). There are also some news clippings about George Bush and some manuscripts and notes about the New Jerusalem Church in the third series of papers (Box 12). Cabell was also interested in John Randolph of Roanoke and there is one folder of letters from him to miscellaneous correspondents about Randolph (Box 8).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series: 1) Correspondence of Joseph C. Cabell (Boxes 1-5); 2) Correspondence of the Bolling, Cabell and Related families (Boxes 6-11); and 3) Legal, Financial and Miscellaneous Papers (Boxes 11-12). The family had bundled the correspondence chiefly by correspondent name and this arrangement has been refined and preserved.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence of Joseph C. Cabell
  - Edward Carrington Cabell (1816-1896) to his uncle, Joseph C. Cabell 1850-1854 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. Hannah Carrington Cabell (1751-1817) to her son, Joseph C. and Mary C. Cabell 1806-1817, 2 folders, 65 items (Box 1)
  - Dr. John Grattan Cabell to his uncle, Joseph C. Cabell 1851-1855, 6 items (Box 1)
  - Joseph C. Cabell (1778-1856) to John Hartwell Cocke (1780-1866) 1810-1848, 5 folders, 175 items (Box 1)
  - Joseph C. Cabell to Isaac A. Coles 1800-1822, 2 folders, 29 items (Box 2)
  - Joseph C. Cabell to his nephew, Nathaniel Francis Cabell 1846-1855, n.d., 2 folders, 155 items (Box 2)
  - Joseph C. Cabell to his parents, Nicholas (1750-1803) and Hannah Carrington Cabell, including one letter to his brother, Dr. George Cabell 1801-1802, 6 items (Box 2)
  - Joseph C. Cabell to Judge St. George Tucker (1775-1861) 1807-1819, 4 items (Box 2)
  - Joseph C. Cabell to William Wirt 1817-1827, 5 items (Box 2)
  - Landon Cabell to Joseph C. Cabell 1808-1832, 5 items (Box 2)
  - Dr. Robert G. Cabell to his uncle, Joseph C. Cabell 1837-1855, 11 items (Box 2)
  - William H. Cabell to his brother, Joseph C. Cabell 1802-1821, 4 folders, 169 items (Box 2)
  - William H. Cabell to his brother, Joseph C. Cabell 1822-1850, 6 folders, 132 items (Box 3)
  - Dr. George Callaway to Joseph C. Cabell 1821-1822, 5 items (Box 3)
  - Mathew Carey to Joseph C. Cabell 1828-1839, 11 items (Box 3)
  - John Coalter to Joseph C. Cabell, including three letters from Cabell in reply 1808-1839, 3 folders, 50 items (Box 3)
  - John Hartwell Cocke to Joseph C. Cabell, including two letters from Mrs. A.B. Cocke to Mrs. Mary Cabell 1807-1855, 9 folders, 199 items (Box 4)
  - Isaac A. Coles to Joseph C. Cabell 1802-1832, 2 folders, 40 items (Box 4)
  - Mayo Cabell to Joseph C. Cabell 1824-1847, n.d., 4 items (Box 5)
  - Malcolm F. Crawford to Joseph C. Cabell 1822-1832, 5 items (Box 5)
  - William J. Lewis (1766-1828) to Joseph C. Cabell 1815-1819, 6 items (Box 5)
  - Thomas S. McLelland (1777-1835) to Joseph C. Cabell 1802-1832, 16 items (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: B-C 1809-1851 (Box 5)
    These include: Thomas Brown (1809); Apsley Butler (1823); Dr. George Cabell (1815); Julia M. Cabell (1851); Mary Cabell, wife of Joseph Cabell (1821); Patrick H. Cabell (1825); Samuel Campbell (1822); James Caskie (1850); Mrs. Louisa Cocke (1827); James P. Cocke (1811); William E. Cunningham (1836); Robert N. Crittenden (1849, 2 items)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: D-G 1810-1840 (Box 5)
    These include: Thomas R. Dew, 1802-1846, (1837-1838, 3 items); William H. Digges (1836); Thomas Dobson, Philadelphia bookbinder (1817, 3 items); Robert W. [Elsom?] (1840); John W. Greene (1810)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: H 1811-1837 (Box 5)
    These include: John Hall (1815); John W. Harris (1837); Edmund Harrison (1811-1819, 3 items); James Harrison (1814): Randolph Harrison (1811-1819, 3 items); James E. Heath (1831-1834, 3 items); William C. Holt (1823); Thomas C. Hoomes (1818-1821, 2 items); General John P. Hungerford (1811)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: L-M 1807-1850 (Box 5)
    These include: Samuel Leake (1828); Mrs. Paulina LeGrand (1815-1816, 2 items); Thomas Massie (1814, 1825, 1834, 4 items); Charles F. Mercer (1820, 1833); Hugh Mercer (1807, 1829, 2 items); John Millington (1836); Garritt Minor (1832, 2 items); William M. Moody (1834); Charles L. Mosby (1837, 1850, 3 items)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: N-P 1808-1854 (Box 5)
    These include: Judge William Nelson (1809-1810, 2 items); Wilson C. Nicholas (1808, 1820, 2 items); Thomas Ogle, carriage maker (1810); T. Oldham (1849); Reuben B. Patterson (1833); Lukens Pierce (1854); Colonel Charles Perrow (1835); William B. Phillips (1825); James Pleasants (1822, includes an enclosure from Governor Dickerson concerning a flax breaking machine); John P. Pleasants (1810); Samuel Pleasants (1813); James P. Preston (1816); General John Preston (1814)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: R-S 1814-1851 (Box 5)
    These include: Archibald Ritchie (1822); James Robertson, with copy of a draft from Cabell (1816, 1818, 3items); Merritt M. Robinson (1831); Sankay & Street (1832); James W. Saunders (1850); Robert G. Scott (1835-1836, 2 items); R.J. Smith, Richmond bookseller (1833); Dr. William Southall (1818); George W. Spooner (1851); John Stokely (1814); Colonel Park Street (1818)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: T 1807-1850 (Box 5)
    These include: John Taliaferro (1829, address leaf only); R.L. Taliaferro (1829); Cephas Thompson (1811); R.B. Townley (1850); Beverley Tucker (1807); George Tucker (1824); Henry W. Tucker (1826); N. B. Tucker (1838, 2 items)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents to Joseph C. Cabell: U-Y 1801-1835 (Box 5)
    These include: John D. Urquhart (1829); D.B. Warden (1833); James Webster (1819); Thomas H. White (1835); Thomas W. White (1831-1832, 3 items); Bennett Wright (1833); David Yancey (1801)
  - Robert Rives to Joseph C. Cabell 1808-1832, 14 items (Box 5)
  - Henry St. George Tucker to Joseph C. Cabell 1800-1814, and 1834-1838, 20 items (Box 5)
  - Charles Yancey to Joseph C. Cabell 1810-1836, 24 items (Box 5)
- Series II: Correspondence of the Cabell and Related Families
  - Jane Bolling to her father, William Bolling 1845, 6 items (Box 6)
  - Sally F. Cocke Brent to Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell 1837, 1856-1862, n.d., 3 folders, 154 items (Box 6)
  - Sally F. Cocke Brent and Arthur Lee Brent to Nathaniel Francis Cabell 1834-1865, 10 items (Box 6)
  - The Reverend George Bush (1796-1859) to Nathaniel Francis Cabell 1845-1859, n.d., 47 items (Box 6)
  - Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell to her husband, Nathaniel Francis Cabell 1832-1861, n.d., 2 folders, 115 items (Box 6)
  - Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell to her son, Philip B. Cabell 1846-1861, n.d., 60 items (Box 6)
  - Elizabeth Nicholas Cabell to her mother, Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell 1852-1857, 3 folders, 118 items (Box 6)
  - Elizabeth Nicholas Cabell to her mother, Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell 1858-1861, n.d., 4 folders, 218 items (Box 7)
  - Elizabeth Nicholas Cabell to her brother, Philip B. Cabell 1843-1856, n.d., 35 items (Box 7)
  - Dr. John Grattan Cabell to his cousin, Nathaniel Francis Cabell 1861-1863, 11 items (Box 7)
  - Mary W. Cabell to her cousin, Nathaniel Francis Cabell 1866-1874, 9 items (Box 7)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his wife, Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell 1831-1848,n.d., 82 items (Box 7)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his father-in-law, John Hartwell Cocke 1834-1848, n.d., 2 folders, 86 items (Box 7)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his son, Philip B. Cabell 1846-1863, 1875-1886, n.d., 2 folders, 103 items (Box 7)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to the Reverend Richard De Charms 1838-1860, n.d., 2 folders, 87 items (Box 8)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to Miscellaneous Correspondents, including drafts 1831-1881, 27 items (Box 8)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to Miscellaneous Correspondents re John Randolph of Roanoke 1868-1878, 8 items (Box 8)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell to his cousin, Isaac Read 1862-1884, 15 items (Box 8)
  - Nathaniel Francis Cabell and Miscellaneous Correspondents, writing to or about the Reverend George Bush 1845-1872, 19 items (Box 8)